בוקר טוב. Boker tov. Today's דף Daf י"ז Yud Zayin and we
continue with the procedure for the סוטה. Sotah. So we have top
of the דף, Daf, משנה. Mishnah. We had just discussed the whole
issue about the collecting of the dirt and putting it into the
vessel and different questions about the dirt, where should the dirt be
coming from, dirt being visible on the top of the vessel, on
the top of the water, and so on. So as
you've remember she had brought her מנחה Minchah and now this is
pretty much following the order of the פסוקים Pesukim she had brought
her מנחה Minchah and now we're getting ready to make her drink,
but first we have to scrape the parchment into the water. So
let's take a look top of י"ז עמוד א. Yud Zayin Amud
Aleph. בא לו לכתוב את המגילה, Ba lo lichtov et haMegillah,
he came to write the מגילה. Megillah. The כהן, Kohen, thank you.
Yes. That's a good question. I think the פסוק Pasuk is וכתב,
V'katav, right? I think it's going on the כהן, Kohen, but it's
an interesting question whether that's מעכב. Me'akeiv. בא לו לכתוב את המגילה,
Ba lo lichtov et haMegillah, he came to write the מגילה. Megillah.
מאיזה מקום הוא כותב? Me'eizeh makom hu kotev? From starting from where
does he write? So actually thank you Michael for opening up let
me actually read to you the פסוקים, Pesukim, okay, and here we
go. It says like this.
So let's actually we might as well this is a good point
anyway to stop and talk about the order of the משניות Mishnayot
and the order of the פסוקים Pesukim in the פרשת הסוטה. Parshat
haSotah. והביא האיש את אשתו אל הכהן והביא את קרבנה עליה עשירת
האיפה קמח שערים. V'hevia ha'ish et ishto el haKohen v'hevia et korbanah
aleiha asirit ha'eifah kemach se'orim. So
our פרק Perek started with discussing the מנחה. Minchah. לא יצק עליו
שמן ולא יתן עליו לבנה כי מנחת קנאת הוא מנחת זכרון מזכרת
עון. Lo yitzok alav shemen v'lo yitein alav levonah ki minchat kena'ot
hu minchat zikaron mazkeret avon. Okay,
so that was bringing the מנחה Minchah but not yet offering it
up because we didn't yet describe in our משנה Mishnah yet either
offering it up. והקריב אתה הכהן והעמידה לפני ה'. V'hikriv otah haKohen
v'he'emidah lifnei Hashem. ולקח הכהן מים קדשים בכלי חרש, V'lakach haKohen mayim
kedoshim bichli chares, water. ומן העפר אשר יהיה בקרקע המשכן יקח הכהן
ונתן אל המים. Umin he'afar asher yihyeh b'karka haMishkan yikach haKohen v'natan
el hamayim. So
the dirt is in the water. That's what we did in the
previous משנה. Mishnah. והעמיד הכהן את האשה לפני ה' ופרע את ראש
האשה ונתן על כפיה את מנחת הזכרון מנחת קנאת היא וביד הכהן
יהיו מי המרים המאררים. V'he'emid haKohen et ha'ishah lifnei Hashem ufarat rosh
ha'ishah v'natan al kapeha et minchat hazikaron minchat kena'ot hi uvyad haKohen
yihyu mei hamarim ham'ererim.
So here it says making her stand and undoing her, disheveling her
hair, which we actually had mentioned much earlier in the process. And
then it says the following. והשביע אתה הכהן. V'hishpia otah haKohen.
The כהן Kohen shall make her take an oath. ואמר אל האשה
אם לא שכב איש אתך ואם לא שטית טמאה תחת אישך. V'amar
el ha'ishah im lo shachav ish otach v'im lo satit tumah tachat
ishech. If no man slept with you, הנקי ממי המרים המאררים
האלה, hinaki mi'mei hamarim ham'ererim ha'eleh, you should be cleansed from these
bitter cursing waters. ואת כי שטית תחת אישך וכי נטמאת. V'at ki
satit tachat ishech v'chi nitmet.
And of course here the funny word is כי, Ki, because כי
Ki can mean if, but it also has a little bit of
a suggestion of because. There's a like again a little bit of
that issue we've been talking about of that presumption of guilt. So
while it starts with if not, you know, there's also the if
here with a little bit of a heavier weighting on the if.
If a man slept with you, ויתן איש בך את שכבתו מבלעדי
אישך. v'yitein ish bach et shichovto mibaladei ishech. והשביע הכהן את האשה
בשבעת האלה ואמר הכהן לאשה יתן ה' אותך לאלה ולשבעה בתוך עמך
בתת ה' את ירכך נפלת ואת בטנך צבה. V'hishpia haKohen et ha'ishah
b'shvuat ha'alah v'amar haKohen la'ishah yitein Hashem otach l'alah v'lishvuah b'toch amech
b'teit Hashem et yerechech nofelet v'et bitnech tzavah. If all that is
true then יתן ה' אותך לאלה ולשבעה בתוך עמך בתת ה' את
ירכך נפלת ואת בטנך צבה. yitein Hashem otach l'alah v'lishvuah b'toch amech
b'teit Hashem et yerechech nofelet v'et bitnech tzavah. If all that is
true then the Lord make you a curse and an oath among
your people, that the Lord make your thigh to fall away and
your belly to swell. ובאו המים המאררים האלה במעיך לצבות בטן ולנפל
ירך. Uva'u hamayim ham'arerim ha'eleh b'me'ayich latzbot beten v'lanpil yerech. So your
belly shall swell up. ואמרה האשה אמן אמן. V'amrah ha'ishah amen amen.
וכתב את האלת האלה הכהן בספר ומחה אל מי המרים. V'katav et
ha'alot ha'eleh haKohen basefer umachah el mei hamarim. The כהן Kohen writes
these in a book and he scrapes it into the water and
then והשקה את האשה V'hishkah et ha'ishah and he makes her drink
it. Okay, so it makes her visit, orally take an oath, then
he writes it down, then he scrapes it. Now here interestingly the
משנה Mishnah skipped over him orally making her take the oath. It
jumps straight to the writing of the oath, which is interesting to
note. So let's keep that in mind. So let's again see what
the משנה Mishnah says. בא לו לכתוב את המגילה, Ba lo lichtov
et haMegillah, he came to write the מגילה. Megillah. מאיזה מקום הוא
כותב? Me'eizeh makom hu kotev? So where does he write from? So
it says מואם לא שכב איש אתך, Mi'v'im lo shachav ish otach,
if a man did not sleep with you.
So again that's where it says והשביע הכהן את האשה ואמר לאשה
אם לא שכב איש אתך. V'hishpia haKohen et ha'ishah v'amar la'ishah im
lo shachav ish otach. If a man did not sleep from you,
you should be cleansed from this water. And you, if a man
did, if you did stray from your husband and a man slept
with you. So he goes on and says that whole thing. If
you don't you'll be cleansed, if you do et cetera. ואינו כותב,
V'eino kotev, but he does not write the instruction in the פסוק.
Pasuk. Meaning he only writes what's in the quote marks in the
פסוק, Pasuk, not the instructions. אינו כותב והשביע הכהן את האשה. Eino
kotev v'hishpia haKohen et ha'ishah.
That he doesn't write, right? You should imagine in the פסוקים Pesukim
there are quote marks. If you do not sleep with a man
you will be cleansed and if you did sleep with a man,
and then a man did sleep with you, and then end of
a quotes and then a hyphen, and the כהן Kohen shall make
her take the שבועת האלה shvuat ha'alah and he shall say to
the woman, and then back to the quote marks. So we're only
going to do the stuff in the quote marks, okay?
Okay and that's the next word that's in the quote marks, right?
So if a man did sleep with you, skip the instruction. Then
יתן ה' אותך לאלה ולשבעה בתוך עמך ובאו המים המאררים האלה במעיך
לצבות בטן ולנפל ירך. yitein Hashem otach l'alah v'lishvuah b'toch amech uva'u
hamayim ham'arerim ha'eleh b'me'ayich latzbot beten v'lanpil yerech. So he'll give the
whole quote without the instructions he has in the middle. ואינו כותב
ואמרה האשה אמן אמן V'eino kotev v'amrah ha'ishah amen amen and he
doesn't write at the end where the woman responds אמן אמן, Amen
Amen, because that's not the oath, that's just her response. That's a
very logical position.
What do you
do...
Maybe that's reflecting Michael's concern. It's true, it's really not part of
the oath, it's just "and the הכהן hakohein shall make her take,"
but maybe he's got a problem, you don't want to cut something
out from the middle of a פסוק. pasuk. So you just write
straight. It's true you might stop before the אשה ishah shall say
אמן אמן, amen amen, but you don't cut out a piece in
the middle. Very interesting. רבי יהודה אומר כל עצמו אינו כותב אלא
ויתן ה׳ אותך לאלה ולשבועה. Rabbi Yehuda omer kol atzmo eino kotev
ela v'yiten Hashem otach l'alah u'lishvuah. He does not write the beginning,
"if a man did not sleep with you, you will be clean,
and if a man did sleep with you," he only writes, he
doesn't write any of the conditions, and he doesn't write any of
the possibility that she's innocent. He only writes the one line, which
is the curse line, which is יתן ה׳ אותך לאלה ולשבועה בתוך
עמך ובאו המים המאררים האלה במעיך. yiten Hashem otach l'alah u'lishvuah b'toch
amech u'va'u hamayim hamarerim ha'eileh b'me'ayich. That's the second והשביע. v'hishbia. Right,
right.
You only write, he doesn't, the first line is if you didn't
sleep, you'll be innocent, and if you did, so that's a) the
possibility of innocence, b) the framing that this oath is conditional on
the fact that you did commit adultery. He skips all of that.
He just writes the oath, the curse. Let you, let your belly
shall swell etc. Okay, כל עצמו. kol atzmo.
What is that?
כל עצמו kol atzmo is like an idiom. It means his whole
point is only to, or like רש״י Rashi says that you should
be very careful to do nothing but write only the phrase of
the curse. Okay. ואינו כותב ואמרה האשה אמן אמן. v'eino kotev v'amra
ha'ishah amen amen. He agrees she does not write אמן אמן. amen
amen. So again, within רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, we've been talking all
along about how the משניות mishnayot have this presumption of guilt. They
haven't even talked about the process being one to clarify her innocence,
the process is all one of to punish her for her guilt.
That's been the presumption of the משניות, mishnayot, and that's certainly reflected
in רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, who does not even have that the
oath that's being written has the possibility that she's innocent. It only
focuses on the one curse line at the end. What's missing also
is, thank you Michael, is that it does not have the oral
part of him reciting it orally and her saying אמן אמן, amen
amen, it sort of just goes straight to the writing.
Yes? I just, I don't know if that necessarily represents a presumption
of guilt as much as what is the goal in the, like
there might be all of that beforehand, the conditional, but like when
we're talking about
the water, the water only has... Right,
right. That could be. Meaning the water is the cursed water. What
makes it curse is that line of the curse. If it's there
then there's... Right, right, right. But it also makes, it also makes
the function of the water, if you still want to think that
the power of the verse is being put into the water, then
the water itself is also conditional. Because if she's innocent, right, then
she's cleansed and the water is ונקתה ונזרעה זרע. v'niktah v'nizre'ah zara.
So to not have those words, as it were, in the water,
is I think a little problematic. Yes?
Is there been a decision which version the הלכה halacha follows?
Well, we're going to see. No, the גמרא Gemara is going to
say where their debate comes from in terms of how they read
the פסוקים. pesukim. So we're going to take a look. Okay. But
again, quite fascinating that it does not have the oral
part of him reciting it orally and her saying אמן אמן, amen
amen, it sort of just goes straight down into her drinking the
water.
This מחלוקת machloket of what you write might reflect the different attitudes
towards this ordeal. In other words, רבי יהודה's Rabbi Yehuda opinion is
the most magical, right, in a way. You're just putting the curse
in the water. When you write more of the conditionality, it makes
it more rational, in a way. It's more legal. It's not just
emphasizing... Aha. You know what I'm saying?
Yeah, I don't know if I would say, because either way I
don't see how it's much
more rational, but I do see, but I think it de-emphasizes the
presumption of guilt. It makes it more of a question about trying
to test whether she's innocent or not, rather than just to punish
her for her guilt. But yeah, there's also... yeah, anyway, but I
think we're saying close to the same thing.
Go ahead. By the way, the next משנה mishnah or two משניות
mishnayot later on י״ח, Yud Chet, Mara's משנה mishnah is על מה
היא אומרת אמן אמן. al mah hi omeret amen amen. Okay, so
it gets to her saying אמן אמן, amen amen, but again, it's
interesting that our משניות mishnayot don't discuss her actually taking the oath,
just goes straight to the actual writing of the curse. Okay, so
let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara.
במאי קמיפלגי? B'mai kamifligi? What are they arguing about? In terms of
which part is written in the water? Where do they get their
debate based on the verse? So, בהאי קרא קמיפלגי. be'hai kra kamifligi.
The following verse: וכתב את האלות האלה הכהן בספר. v'chatav et ha'alot
ha'eileh hakohein basefer. He shall write these curses in the scroll. רבי
מאיר סבר Rabbi Meir savar
אלות, alot, the curses, are אלות ממש, alot mamash, the part that
says that she's to be cursed. Okay. האלות, Ha'alot, the extra ה,
hey, is לריבוי, l'ribui, expanding the things that are written. לרבות קללות
הבאות מחמת ברכות. L'rabot klalot haba'ot machamat brachot. The curses that come
that are by inference by the blessing. Well, they're not really a
blessing, but it's הנקה מימי המאררים. hinaki mimei hamarerim. If you're innocent,
you will be cleansed. So that's an implicit curse. If you're not
innocent, you won't be cleansed, you'll be punished. Because here's what he
says. Meaning, what would our presumption have been? What would our presumption
without the משנה mishnah have been? That he writes the beginning of
what he says, right? "If you're innocent, let you be cleansed," because
the תורה Torah says... As you shall write the curses, and being
innocent is not a curse. Maybe that's somewhat of your point, Jenna,
right?
So therefore, how do you know to include the beginning of the
oath, the conditional part of being innocent since that's not a curse?
And the תורה Torah *Torah* only says write the curse and scrape
it into the water. Right. So therefore he says, okay fine, the
ה hei *hay* means even the stuff that's like the implicit curse.
Being innocent is an implicit curse because if
you're—if you're innocent be cleansed is an implicit curse because if you're
guilty you won't be cleansed. Okay, but the extra ה hei, *hay*
comes to include the first part of the statement which is not
itself a curse.
What do you think about the possibility of the word מגילה megillah
*Megillah* in לשון חכמים *Lashon Hakhamim* for ספר sefer. *Sefer*, which is
לשון מקרא *Lashon Mikra*?
No, that isn't true. Wait a minute. Is מגילה megillah, *Megillah* in
the תנך *Tanakh*, isn't it?
It's not in the—Wait, in אסתר *Esther*.
Yeah, and it's also not in ירמיהו *Yirmiyahu* when they write that
מגילת *Megillat*—yeah.
So it's an interesting switch here.
Right, but I think a ספר Sefer *Sefer* includes a much larger
corpus, this is just a small scroll with a few a few
sentences.
Right, but the תורה Torah *Torah* calls it a ספר Sefer *Sefer*.
The תורה Torah *Torah* calls it a ספר sefer, *Sefer*. Yeah, right.
I mean the תורה Torah *Torah* calls a גט get. *Get* a
ספר *Sefer*. But yes. Okay, anyway...
Wait, or they write it on parchment?
Oh, that's the next משנה mishnah. *Mishna*. Okay, let's focus. Okay, so
anyway, so the extra ה hei *hay* come to include that the
first part of the oath, which is not itself a curse, but
it's the flip side of the curse. רבות קללות הבאות מחמת ברכות
*Rabos klolos habos machmas brachos*. אלה eleh *Eileh*, now these curses is
limiting. למעוטי קללות שבמשנה תורה Torah, *L'ma'utei klolos she'be'Mishneh Torah*. Don't just
write any curses, okay? Write curses, so משנה Mishnah. תורה Torah, *Mishneh
Torah*, right, there's a whole section there where it says about, right,
where it says, you know, what is it, כי תשא *Ki Tisa*
or something? Not כי תשא *Ki Tisa*. כי תבוא *Ki Tavo*, where
it's all about like all the curses that will come to you,
and it there uses the
phrase—obviously, well that's what אלה *Eileh* is. These curses. Exactly, that's exactly
the point, so aren't you glad that it's פשט *pshat*? Okay, so
it says, right, so there it says, והיה בשמעו את et, דברי
האלה ha-eleh הזאת והתברך בלבבו לאמר *v'hayah b'shomo es divrei ha'alah hazos
v'hisbareich bilvavo leimor*, so there it's even called an אלה *alah*, right?
So it even uses the label of אלה *alah*. למעוטי *L'ma'utei* okay,
שבמשנה תורה *she'be'Mishneh Torah*. האלה ha-eleh *Ha'eileh*, the double the's, the these
or whatever, the double limit, למעוטי צואות וקבלות אמן *l'ma'utei tzava'os v'kabalos
amen*. Only the curse part, not the instructional part to the כהן
*Kohen*, and not the woman's response אמן אמן *amen amen*. So that's
a very nice explanation. Okay, ורבי יוסי *v'Rabbi Yose*, רבי יוסי *Rabbi
Yose* with a כולה כדאמר *kulah k'damar*, I agree with the entire
way you דרשן darshan *darshaned* the פסוק pasuk, *pasuk*, except I don't
agree to include the positive part at the beginning, that's not a
curse. Okay, את et לרבות *Es l'rabos*, oh I'm sorry. No no.
No no he did, I'm sorry, I'm jumping ahead. He did include
the positive part. What did רבי *Rabbi*—oh, רבי יוסי *Rabbi Yose* said
you didn't skip over the part in the middle. You didn't skip
over the instruction in the middle. את לרבות *Es l'rabos*, the את
*Es*, את האלות האלה ha-alot ha-eleh *Es ha'alos ha'eileh*, לרבות צואות וקבלות
*l'rabos tzava'os v'kabalos* to include the instruction to the כהן *Kohen*. Oh,
it looks like רבי יוסי *Rabbi Yose* would have actually, right, את
האלות ha'alot? האלה ha-eleh *Es ha'alos ha'eileh*. So it looks like when
רבי יוסי *Rabbi Yose* says לא היה מפסיק *lo hayah mafsik*, Michael,
you should be very happy, it doesn't only mean he didn't skip
over the part in the middle, I actually think I misstated this
when I read the משנה Mishnah. *Mishna*, it seems like you're saying
he would even end the end of the פסוק pasuk *pasuk* ואמרה
האשה אמן אמן *v'amrah ha'ishah amen amen*. So he actually, exactly Michael's
concern, like you don't chop a פסוק pasuk. *pasuk* in half. So
he basically, he starts from the beginning, but I don't know, but
the גמרא gemara *Gemara*'s saying his reason is את *Es*. Okay, so
I completely agree with the way you've read it. האלות *Ha'alos* it
means even the positive part in the beginning, and אלה *Eileh* just
means don't go any, don't do anything else, but what I don't
agree is that you excluded the instructional part. I think the word
את *Es* is coming to include the instructional part and include where
the woman says אמן אמן *amen amen* at the end. They'd actually
have a problem with this, because it's like God telling you what
to do, you know what I mean? But I understand. So רבי
מאיר rabbi Meir *Rabbi Meir*, and now what would רבי מאיר rabbi
Meir *Rabbi Meir* say back? אתין לא דריש *Es-in lo darish*. He's
not impressed with the את *Es*. That doesn't come to include anything.
Okay, so they both agree you start with the positive part of
the curse, and the question is do you cut out the instruction
and the woman's saying of אמן אמן *amen amen*? ורבי יהודה *v'Rabbi
Yehuda*, now
רבי
יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda*'s the
one that skips
the entire beginning
and just goes to the punchline
at
the
end.
So כולהו במיעוטי דרשי להו
*kulu b'mi'utei darshai lehu*.
Every extra letter that you focused on or phrase, some of them
you used to include, some to exclude, he uses everything to exclude,
everything to be very narrow. אלות alot, *Alos*, אלות alot ממש *alos
mamash*. אלות alot *Alos* is only the curse part. Okay, האלות *Ha'alos*,
which you said was including the positive stuff in the beginning, no,
the ה hei *hay* is excluding. למעוטי קללות הבאות מחמת ברכות *L'ma'utei
klolos habos machmas brachos*. For him, it's exactly saying only the curses,
not the stuff in the beginning, which isn't a curse, which is
a blessing, or at least it's a non-curse. Okay, אלה *Eileh* these,
למעוטי קללות שבמשנה תורה *l'ma'utei klolos she'be'Mishneh Torah*. האלה *Ha'eileh*, למעוטי צואות
וקבלות *l'ma'utei tzava'os v'kabalos*, האלה *Ha'eileh* include even the instruction and the
saying of אמן *amen*. So he basically agrees with the first approach,
that you cut out the instruction and the saying of אמן *amen*,
but the האלות *Ha'alos* is coming to say not the blessing part
at the beginning, or the whatever the non-curse part in the beginning.
Only the curse part. ורבי מאיר *V'Rabbi Meir*, now רבי מאיר rabbi
Meir *Rabbi Meir* who includes the הנקי *hi-naki*, be cleansed at the
beginning, מאי שנא האי ה hei, *mai shna hai hay*, the ה
hei *hay* of האלות *Ha'alos*... אלות alot. דמרבי ביה, de-marbi bei, he
says that's coming to include even more than just the curse part,
the if you're innocent part. ומאי שנא האי ה, u-mai shna hai
hei, the ה heh, of האלה דמיעוטי ביה, de-mi'utei bei, that's coming
to exclude, right? האלה excludes the instructional. So there's an extra ה,
heh, inclusive or exclusive, including or excluding. So the גמרא gemara says,
well look, it depends on context. ה דגבי דריבוייא, hei de-gabei de-ribuiya,
when it comes with a word that's including, אלות, alot. אלות is
coming to tell you the אלות is what you do say. It's
not coming to limit, it's coming to say you say the אלות.
So an extra ה expands the אלות. ריבוייא היא, ribuiya hi, it
expands not only the curses, but even the implicit curses, the beginning
of the statement. ה דגבי דמיעוטא, hei de-gabei de-mi'uta, when it's by
a word that's limiting, אלה is the only these, nothing else. So
the extra ה comes to reinforce the limit, מיעוטא mi'uta is coming
to reinforce the limit and it's coming to say not even the
instructional part. Okay, so basically what do we have? We have based
on different sort of pickup, whether you how you read a ה,
how you read an את, either you're going to come basically say
you do the whole thing, you don't cut out any part of
the פסוק, pasuk. which as Michael might be saying might reflect a
general attitude of not chopping up פסוקים. pesukim. Or you might be
saying you just cut out the instructional part because that's not actually
in quote marks. Or you might just say and you use the
word of like האלה to cut out the instructional part and only
the actual curse itself. Or you might come to say there's all
the things, האלות האלה is being very, very specific and it's only
the curse part at the end. With all these cases, it was
sort of an issue we raised yesterday about do you sort of
start with your conclusion and work backwards to connect it to the
פסוק pasuk or are you actually deriving it? Like is this really
hermeneutic differences here? Is this really a difference that one person always
דרשן את and the other person has different approaches to whether you
see a ה in this context or that context? Or do we
start with an intuition, right? That is true. I mean נחום איש
גמזו Nachum Ish Gamzu and so on. But the question is like
is this like did we start with the different hermeneutics or did
we start with a different intuition in terms of what's going to
be written? Right? Like one says like maybe like Michael said, you
can't interrupt the פסוק. pasuk Another approach is well it's only the
curse. The other approach is well maybe she's innocent, maybe you have
to have both components in there, right? So how much did you
sort of start with an intuition about where about what makes sense
and how much was it just purely derived from a hermeneutic that
they already had before they even approached the פסוקים? pesukim?
But let's say you had a you called it an intuition, let's
say you had a sense that it was
stronger than just an intuition that that you're not allowed to cut
a פסוק. pasuk Right, why would you need a hermeneutic?
You're right, maybe you wouldn't if you had that. I mean unless
you felt that the פסוק pasuk overrode it. I mean sometimes פסוקים
pesukim override certain things. But you're right. And I shouldn't say by
any of those it's an
intuition. By maybe it's just a particular intuition is like a little
not specific. Like maybe it's a particular philosophy
about what's going on here, what are the mechanics here. So the
גמרא gemara sort of attributes it all to these hermeneutics. Okay, so
now the גמרא gemara continues. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like
this. והא לית ליה לרבי מאיר מכלל לאו אתה שומע
הן. ve-ha leit lei le-rabbi Meir mi-klal lav attah shomea hen. One
minute. רבי מאיר rabbi Meir normally does not say that from the
negative you can infer the positive. By the way, רבי מאיר rabbi
Meir wasn't mentioned in the משנה. Mishnah He's just assumed to be
the תנא קמא. tanna kamma. Okay. Now why is this relevant? Because
רבי מאיר if you remember said that the way we included the
line in the beginning, "if you didn't you should be innocent", why
is it included? That's not a curse. Because it's an implicit curse.
Because if you did, then you should be punished and found guilty.
Okay, but that's saying from the one statement you can infer the
inverse.
If you're innocent you should be cleansed. So that suggests if you're
guilty you shouldn't be cleansed. But that's מכלל לאו אתה שומע הן
mi-klal lav attah shomea hen or מכלל הן אתה שומע לאו. mi-klal
hen attah shomea lav.
And רבי מאיר says you cannot infer the inverse from one sentence
to the next. Now where does he say this? He says this
by making conditions about a תנאי. tenai. Right, if you think about
משה Moshe says to בני גד ובני ראובן, bnei gad u-bnei reuven,
he needs a תנאי כפול. tenai kaful. It says, what's the פסוק
pasuk. about אם יעברו חלוצים לפני אחיכם בני ישראל ונאחזו בתוככם בארץ
כנען ואם לא יעברו, im ya'avru chalutzim lifnei acheikhem bnei Yisrael ve-ne'achzu
be-tokhekhem be-eretz kena'an ve-im lo ya'avru, like and if you don't pass
in front of that, then you shall not be you shall not
get
מעבר לירדן me-ever la-Yarden etc. You shall be and so on. So
therefore it was a double תנאי. tenai. If you do this you'll
get it, if you don't do this you won't get it. Why
did you need this double תנאי? tenai? So do you in general
by a when you make conditions need it to be doubled? So
רבי מאיר basically says yes, you generally need conditions to be doubled
because you don't say מכלל לאו אתה שומע הן. mi-klal lav attah
shomea hen. Now actually for any of those who took propositional logic
in college, you will know that this is actually correct, that if
you say if p then q does not mean if not p
then not q. If it rains we won't play ball doesn't mean
if it doesn't rain we will play ball. It just means that
if it rains we won't play ball. If it doesn't rain we
might, we might not. Who knows, right? All if P then Q
means is that if not Q then not P. If it rains,
we don't play ball means if we did play ball, it must
be that it didn't rain. Okay? So if you are innocent, if
you have not committed adultery, you shall be innocent. Maybe if you
did commit adultery, you also be cleansed. But who knows what happens
if you did commit adultery? But if you didn't commit adultery, then
for sure you'll be cleansed.
I'm shaking my head though, given everything else the Torah's saying about.
I understand. But that's a general principle that you could not infer,
you know, if P then Q, you cannot assume if not P
then not Q. Okay? So the question is whether when Rabbi Meir,
does Rabbi Meir really say that all the time? Is it like
a way of parsing normal people's statements? Or does he just say
that like in cases of like תנאים Tnaim and conditions and, you
know, a formal requirement when you're making stipulations about whether something takes
effect or not, you have to be a hundred percent crystal clear
and spell out both sides of it? Okay? So the גמרא Gemara
here seems to feel that it's a general principle that Rabbi Meir,
it's not limited to תנאים, Tnaim, because here Rabbi Meir is saying
that if you are doing the, you know, if you did not
commit adultery, you'll be innocent, is an implicit curse. It implicitly is
cursed that if you did commit adultery, you'll be punished. And versus
Rabbi Meir doesn't believe that that's implicit in the statement. Okay? He
does not believe. So it sounds like it's not just a question
about the formal requirement of תנאים. Tnaim. Maybe here it is also
a תנאי. Tnai. I know it's a תנאי. Tnai.
So maybe it is, but he also generalizes that.
I understand. Maybe it is, maybe it is. But it's also, but
again, here the only question is, is it included in the concept
of this is also an implicit curse because it says האלות? So
is this statement an implicit curse when it says if you didn't
do it, you'll be innocent? And the גמרא Gemara says, how could
Rabbi Meir say it's an implicit curse? Rabbi Meir says you don't
say מכלל לאו אתה שומע הן. miklal lav ata shome'a hen. So
let's take a look at what the גמרא Gemara says. להא לית
ליה לרבי מאיר,
Leha
leit
lei l'Rabbi Meir, it's an implicit curse, right? If you say מכלל
לאו אתה שומע הן. miklal lav ata shome'a hen. להא לית ליה
לרבי מאיר מכלל לאו אתה שומע הן. Leha leit lei l'Rabbi Meir
miklal lav ata shome'a hen. So how could you call this an
implicit curse? So אמר רבי תנחום, Amar Rabbi Tanchum, חינקי כתיב. chinaki
ktiv. It says be cleansed. What does that mean? So רש״י Rashi
says it's a little play on word which says חינקי, chinaki, you
should be strangled. Okay? So the פסוק pasuk says אם לא שכב
איש אותך ואם לא שטית טומאה תחת אישך חינקי, im lo shachav
ish otach v'im lo satit tumah tachat ishech chinaki, but you could
just take, cut off the im of the פסוק pasuk, and write
טומאה תחת אישך חינקי. tumah tachat ishech chinaki. If you impurefied yourself
under your husband, you should be strangled. Okay? So anyway, that makes
it a little less implicit, and that's how come it's included under
the rubric of a curse because it has that double entendre going
on there. Okay, but the גמרא Gemara, doesn't say that at all.
I understand. Okay. דרש רבי עקיבא. Darash Rabbi Akiva. Rabbi Akiva made
the following דרשה. drasha. איש ואישה, Ish v'ishah, man and woman, זכו
zachu if they merit, שכינה ביניהם, shechinah beineihem, the divine name is
between them, the יוד yud and the ה, right? I'm sure nobody
has ever heard this דרשה drasha before. Okay. לא זכו Lo zachu
if they do not merit, so and the God's presence is not
between them, so אש אוכלתן, esh ochaltan, then a fire will consume
them. Okay? So and by the way, interesting רש״י. Rashi. If you
look at רש״י, Rashi, זכו, zachu, if you look at רש״י, Rashi,
three lines, right, you take the יוד yud and the ה, you
left with אש. esh. Look at the רש״י Rashi three lines before
it gets why, זכו zachu ללכת בדרך ישרה, lalechet bederech yesharah, to
go on the straight path, שלא יהא הוא נואף ולא היא נואפת.
shelo yehei hu no'ef v'lo hi no'efet. He should not be an
adulterer and she not an adulteress. Now again, it's interesting because we're
reintroducing the man as a possible, as the possible adulterer and one
who cheats on his wife. And also in this context, right? It's
an interesting question which,
הלכתית halachically again, a man only commits adultery not when he sleeps
with another woman who's not his wife but when he sleeps with
a married woman. But there is definitely places where the גמרא, Gemara.
where
רש״י, Rashi, other places seem to like ignore the technical legal definition
and talk about in real-world terms. You know, adultery is sleeping with
another woman who's not your wife, and that seems to be the
point here. What? It's only לא זכו lo zachu because he sleeps
with a married woman? That's what he's saying? That he's no, no,
it sounds like if he cheats on his wife, right? If she
cheats on him or he cheats on her. So again, there's something
that's, we're not only sort of equating it and talking about the
possibility of him, you know, also sexual sin, but actually, I think
the implicit sense is even bracketing the imbalance from the legal definition.
You know, whether he's cheating or she's cheating, either way, that's obviously
tearing apart the marriage and then אש אוכלתן. esh ochaltan.
Yes.
What a modern reading of the situation. Did they think that way
back then?
About that he, if he cheats on her?
If it's not legally.
Yeah. So I, I have some, some cases where that does seem
to be reflected. I mean,
but I think you see it more, I don't know how explicit
it is in the גמרא. Gemara I see it sometimes more through
the commentary of רש״י Rashi or תוספות Tosafot and they're coming from
an Ashkenazi monogamous society. So it's an interesting question like how much
can you find black and white evidence in חז״ל Chazal about that.
But, you know, I don't think it's such a far reach from
this point, right? So, so it does sound like, you know, at
least the way רש״י Rashi is reading it is if one of
them cheats on the other, is I think how רש״י Rashi is
reading it. Yes.
You know what
bothers me about this מדרש midrash is it's such a play on.
He's not going on the, I don't think he's going on the
פסוק. pasuk.
Oh, he is not?
I don't think. I don't think he's going on exactly.
In other words, it's a דרשה drasha that must have been.
Yeah, I think it's in the context of talking about סוטה, Sotah,
but I think it's like, I don't think it's specifically about it.
Right, clearly, but like water has been the, we've brought down other
points.
Maybe the water is coming to put out the potential fire that's
glaring. No, but that should work in very well, you know? I
mean, if you actually think about it, because here's the thing that
I was thinking about, and maybe it ties into what you are.
The שכינה ביניהם, shechina beneihem, no no, the שכינה ביניהם, shechina beneihem,
right? Is also אש אוכלה. esh ochla. That's true too, it has
to be אש אוכלה, esh ochla, but I wasn't thinking about that.
So we have a lot of good דרשות drashos here, but what
I was thinking about was that, you know, it's all about God's
name here, right? Erasing God's name. And because they didn't stop it
sooner, God's name is going to be erased. We're about to put
God's name down on the parchment and they're coming through the בית
המקדש Beis Hamikdash where God's presence is. So somehow the presence of
God's name can, you know, can resolve this problem, right? If they
got so far that God wasn't sort of in their marriage yet,
as it were, enough that the problem wasn't resolved ahead of time,
they have to come here and try to bring God more directly
in to get God
to like calm everything down, right? So they're in the בית המקדש,
Beis Hamikdash, they're dealing with God's name, etc., you know, and maybe
you're right, like maybe if it turns into water and the water
douses the fire because she's innocent, then God's name is basically putting
out the fire. That's where, that's where I would sort of see
that here too. And if God's name goes away and ultimately God's
name got erased, you know, whatever, you know, but consumed, but I
think that here the problem is that it's all about trying to
bring God to resolve something because God hasn't been enough part of
the equation to begin with. So that's sort of, but maybe you're
right, maybe the one just that the water, of course the funny
thing is that if she's guilty, it doesn't, she doesn't get consumed
by fire, she gets consumed by water, if she's guilty. But the
water can also douse the fire. Okay, so all right. So אמר
רבא ודאשה עדיפא מדאיש, Amar Rava, ve-d'isha adifa mi-d'ish,
the woman's fire is greater than the
man's. Why do you why? האי מצטרפיס, Hai mitzarfis, because the אלף
שין aleph-shin of the woman, the אש esh is already right there,
the letters are already together. והאי לא מצטרפיס, Ve-hai lo mitzarfis, the
יוד, yud, God's name, is between the אלף aleph and the שין
shin of the man. So what does that mean? Does that mean
that a woman is, does that mean a woman is meaning after
we've done this nice little statement of parity, are we saying that
the woman is though more likely to sin because she's got, you
know, the יצר הרע yetzer hara stronger, the אש esh is stronger,
God's letter doesn't, you know, create as much natural equilibrium? Is that
what we're saying, or we're saying that if they sin, like somehow
I don't know, it, you know, more of I don't know, more
more anger or more of, you know, enmity comes up around the
woman? I mean, רש"י Rashi says ודאשה עדיפא מדאיש אש של אשה
קשה וממהרת לאכול ולהיפרע משל איש. ve-d'isha adifa mi-d'ish, esh shel isha
kasheh u-mi-mahares le-echol u-le-ha-perei-ah mi-shel ish. So does it mean that she's
more likely to sin? Does it mean that when she sins, somehow
punishment will be swifter? It'll have a bigger impact in the marriage?
Remember when the גמרא Gemara says when the woman sins, it undermines
more the household because she's off being with her adulterer and she's
not raising the kids, no, but the גמרא Gemara says before, she's
not raising the kids or making dinner. So so it more directly
hurts the household. So I don't know, meaning I would be inclined
to think just because of the גמרא's Gemara general bias, you know,
towards towards men as more spiritual sort of beings, as it were,
that you know, one way to read this, not necessarily a way
that works with our sensibilities, but one way to read this is
is that the man who is more religiously oriented, you know, and
so on, so he's able to control his, to keep his fire
more calm, you know, so God's name is more in the middle
and calms, you know, separates the powerful forces, where the woman, like
you know, maybe is not so much and the powerful forces are
more, have to be more work needs to be to keep them
under control. But maybe not, you know, maybe you could make different
ways of reading it.
I'm thinking of יהודה ותמר, Yehuda ve-Tamar, הוציאוה ותישרף. Hotzi'uha ve-tisaref.
Yeah, well that's true. Anyway, alright, so let's keep on going. It
says like this. Okay, nine. אמר רבא מפני מה אמרה תורה הביאו
עפר לסוטה Amar Rava, mipnei ma amrah Torah ha-vei afar la-Sotah?
Why does it say bring ashes for the סוטה? Sotah? זכתה יוצא
ממנה בן כאברהם אבינו, Zachtah, yotzei mi-menah ben k'Avraham Avinu,
if she merits, she'll have a son like אברהם אבינו.
Avraham Avinu. דכתיב ביה עפר ואפר. D'chsiv bei afar ve-efer. Okay, so
that's ונקתה ונזרעה
זרע, ve-nik-tah ve-niz-ra'ah zara,
she'll have a meritorious child. לא זכתה תחזור לעפרה, Lo zachtah, tachzor
la-afarah,
go back to the dust. Alright. דרש רבא בשכר שאמר אברהם אבינו
ואנכי
עפר ואפר, Darash Rava, bi-s'char she-amar Avraham Avinu ve-anochi afar ve-efer, now
we're doing עפר ואפר. afar ve-efer.
זכו בניו לשתי מצוות. Zachu banav l'shtei mitzvos. אפר פרה, Efer para,
the ashes of the red heifer, ועפר סוטה, ve-afar Sotah, both of
which you mentioned before. Okay. So the גמרא Gemara says איכא נמי
עפר כיסוי הדם Ika nami afar kisuy hadam? How about that? That's
also a מצוה mitzvah with dust. התם הכשר מצוה איכא הנאה ליכא.
Hasam hachsher mitzvah ika hana'ah leka.
There it's just doing a מצוה. mitzvah. But there’s no benefit. Here
there’s benefit. The ashes of פרה אדומה parah adumah let you become
טהור tahor and the dirt of the סוטה sotah resolves, you know,
fighting between a husband and wife. So there it's not just a
מצווה, mitzvah, but it's actually a מצווה mitzvah that has very concrete
benefit. דרש רבא. Darash Rava.
Okay, we’re by... דרש רבא. Darash Rava. בשכר שאמר אברהם אבינו, Bishchar
she'amar Avraham Avinu, because אברהם Avraham said, אם מחוט ועד שרוך נעל,
im michut v'ad s'roch na'al, if from a string to a shoelace,
you know, I will take from any of the booty of סדום,
Sdom, you know, I won't take any, you know, I just want...
whatever, בלעדי רק
אשר, biladai rak asher, you know, just give me back what the...
what my servants ate and so on. So because he refused expenses,
exactly. So because he refused the booty, זכו בניו לשתי מצוות. zachu
banav l'shtei mitzvot. They got two מצוות. mitzvot. חוט של תכלת, chut
shel techelet, the string of תכלת techelet in the ציצית, tzitzit, ורצועה
של תפילין, v'retzuah shel tefillin, and the strap like a shoelace, especially
if you think it's a sandal strap, it's out of leather, that's
why a shoelace is leather, right, for תפילין. tefillin. So it says
בשלמא bishlama ורצועה של תפילין, v'retzuah shel tefillin,
well let's see what the גמרא Gemara, says. דכתיב וראו כל עמי
הארץ כי שם ה' נקרא עליך. dechtiv v'ra'u kol amei ha'aretz ki
shem Hashem nikra alecha. So again, we’re not just talking about a
מצווה, mitzvah, but a מצווה mitzvah that there’s some concrete this-worldly benefit
to. So תפילין tefillin there’s this-worldly benefit because people see God’s name
is called on you ויראו ממך, v'yaru mimeka, and they’re fearful of
you. ותניא רבי אליעזר הגדול אומר אלו תפילין שבראש, v'tanya Rabbi Eliezer
HaGadol omer elu tefillin shebarosh, and God's name called on you is
the wearing of the תפילין. tefillin. So that’s a very concrete benefit.
אלא חוט של תכלת מאי היא? ela chut shel techelet mai hi?
In what way is wearing... doing the מצווה mitzvah of ציצית tzitzit
and תכלת, techelet, in what way does that give you some concrete
this-worldly benefit? דתניא, detanya, תנא ברייתא, tana baraita, היי רבי מאיר אומר:
hai Rabbi Meir omer: מה נשתנה תכלת מכל מיני צבעונים? mah nishtanah
techelet mikol minei tivonim? Why...
what makes תכלת techelet special from all the other colors? מפני שהתכלת
דומה לים וים דומה לרקיע, mipnei shehatechelet domeh layam v'yam domeh larakia,
because the תכלת techelet is similar to the color of the ocean
and the ocean is similar to the color of the sky, ורקיע
דומה לכסא הכבוד, v'rakia domeh l'chise hakavod, and the sky is similar
to the heavenly throne. דכתיב שנאמר ויראו את אלהי ישראל ותחת רגליו
כמעשה לבנת הספיר, dechtiv shene'emar v'yiru et elohei yisrael v'tachat raglav k'ma'aseh
livnat hasapir, and they saw the God of ישראל Yisrael
and under His legs were like the... like a sapphire construction, וכעצם
השמים לטהר, u'chetsem hashamayim latohar,
like the essence of the sky in purity. So the actual color
of the sky is similar to the color of the divine throne.
וכתיב כמראה אבן ספיר דמות כסא, v'chtiv k'mareh even sapir dmut kise,
and again also says that the sapphire is like the divine throne.
So therefore it inspires you, it connects you to God, it gives
you a glimpse of a vision of God. So it's not... so
it’s a type of a benefit you get other than just the
idea oh, I did a מצווה. mitzvah. There’s something in which it
actually does something to improve your life. Okay, so all these types
of things... I mean, some of the way of improving your life
is in an halachic world, like it makes you טהור. tahor. Okay,
some of it, you know, it makes... these are like,
none of these are they make you wealthy. It makes you טהור,
tahor, it resolves a fight between husband and wife, it makes people
see that you’re connected to God ויראו ממך, v'yaru mimeka, it makes
you more connected to God, but these are very like concrete things
that it does for you, and...
anyway that’s the merit. Now is there some more deeper connection to
אברהם? Avraham? You know, I don’t know, like... you know,
I mean somebody could sort of suggest... I don't know if that's
being suggested here at all, but ואנכי עפר ואפר v'anochi afar v'efer
is, you know, about this sense of being very humble. And very
often sometimes, you know, fights come about and people also...
I mean, not only why fights come about for many reasons, but
often people don't... aren't able to move towards reconciliation because they’re standing
on their pride. And nobody ever actually actually wants to like, you
know, give in or admit that they were wrong or, you know,
move forward. So I think you could definitely see the type of
the sense of עפר afar and the עפר סוטה afar sotah somehow
some sense of like, you know, that somehow maybe it's sometimes it
might be the being a little bit more humble and not standing
on your pride that could allow for a resolution. Of course that's
not what happened here. Here actually he was סותר, soter, she was
denying it, and some miraculous thing that creates the resolution. So I
don’t know if that type of a דרשה derashah works. You know,
I mean by and by the what do you call it, by
the case of אם מחוט ועד שרוך נעל, im michut v'ad s'roch
na'al, right, אברהם Avraham basically says, you shouldn't say that you made
me rich, like God, you know, or I want to be known
that I was through God. And the connection here is basically a
way of acknowledging your connection to God, right? The תפילין tefillin makes
people see you’re connected to God, the תכלת techelet makes you think
about God. So there’s like a better connection with this than with
the other, at least than I’m able to do with the עפר
afar and the אפר, efer, yes.
Do you think maybe we have to be thinking of like also
a little bit of גן עדן, Gan Eden, right? If we’re talking
about women doing things...
oh, yeah, yeah.
I don’t know, like I don’t have it thought out yet, but
I wonder if there’s something...
oh, that’s interesting.
The birth and the breath and the dust... oh, interesting.
Oh, what actually certainly is true because the curse in גן עדן
Gan Eden is about having children with pain and childbirth and so
on. And here the blessing is, right, ונקתה ונזרעה זרע. v'niktah v'nizra'ah
zara. And רש"י Rashi actually quotes on that פסוק pasuk the מדרש
Midrash which says that it doesn’t just mean she can conceive, but
that she’s able to conceive and to give birth without pain. So
that's actually, I never occurred to me, that's actually like a reverse
of the curse of חוה. Chavah. So you're right. Now that also
is not per se sexual sin, although חז"ל Chazal read that as
a type of a sexual sin, they read the נחש nachash as
a seducer and so on.
So and we know there’s also an aspect of like the fact
we're putting dust in the water and like this is like an
epitome of like what women do. like did to men, I don't
know, earlier, you know what I mean?
No, how's that dust in the water?
Because isn't Adam cursed at the...
Oh, because oh you mean בזעת אפיך. be-ze'at apecha. Oh like כי
עפר אתה ואל עפר תשוב. ki-afar ata ve-el afar tashuv.
Right.
Right. Yeah. I mean, yeah, other... I don't see it directly but
there is the whole thing. It is interesting. It is worth pointing
out that prior to the פרשה Parsha of... It is worth pointing
out that prior to the פרשת סוטה, Parshat Sotah, you already have
the phenomenon of dust in water as a test by... by... by
מעשה העגל. Ma'aseh ha-Egel. Moshe grinds up the עגל Egel and he
makes them drink it.
So a whole parallel, right? Don't you see the infidelity?
Right, right. But what that also shows you is, right, exactly, because
right, because right, because committing adultery the תורה already describes, right? About
וזנו אחרי אלהי נכר הארץ. ve-zanu acharei elohei nechar ha-aretz. God is
described as an אל קנא, el kana, a husband who suspects his
wife has committed adultery, ועבר עליו רוח קנאה ve-avar alav ruach kin'ah
and so on. But the fascinating thing there is that that story,
that פרשה Parsha occurs way before the מצוה mitzvah of סוטה, Sotah,
which shows that that idea, that you know,
somehow some type of a water grinding up something in the water
and drinking it as a test for fidelity, right, is something that
precedes the תורה's מצוה mitzvah of the סוטה. Sotah. It was already
there prior to that.
Okay.
Does the רש״ש Rashash also reflect that theological debate of מצוות לאו
ליהנות ניתנו? mitzvot lav le-hanot nitnu?
Possibly, although I see that more as a halakhic discussion, but yes.
Here it definitely does want a מצוה mitzvah that you're getting some
הנאה hana'ah from. That is correct.
Okay. I guess that's how you get the...
Yeah, but you weren't here for that one. Moving on. Okay. Next
משנה. Mishnah אינו כותב לא על הלוח ולא על הנייר. Eino kotev
lo al ha-luach ve-lo al ha-neyar. So now we get to the
question of what constitutes ספר. You do not write on the... on
a לוח, luach, on like a tablet. Okay, רש״י Rashi says a
wooden tablet. Or on נייר, neyar, paper. Paper is basically made out
of like a type of a fiber out of like... out of
trees, papyrus, etc. רש״י Rashi says... what do you call it? Grass
or whatever, but I assume he means a type of a papyrus.
Anyway, some type of a fibrous material. That's not good. ולא על
דפתרא. ve-lo al diphera. דפתרא diphera is untreated קלף klaf or not
fully treated
קלף. klaf. אלא על המגילה, ela al ha-megillah, but on a classic
parchment. It's actually interesting. It should have said, normally the contrast gets
back to your point מגילה megillah. to דפתרא diphera is קלף. klaf.
קלף klaf basically means, you know, parchment, the classically treated parchment that
you would use to write a מגילה, megillah ספר תורה, sefer torah,
תפילין tefillin and so on. So it is interesting here that it
contrasts דפתרא diphera to מגילה. Megillah מגילה Megillah is more like the...
the constructed book, not just the piece of parchment. But you're not
constructing a book here. It's just a single piece of parchment. שנאמר
בספר. she-ne'emar ba-sefer. Okay, and somehow that means only that. ואינו כותב
לא בקומוס. ve-eino kotev lo be-komos. You cannot write... the ink cannot
be something called קומוס, komos, which רש״י Rashi says is some type
of a... of a tree sap. ולא בקנקנתום. ve-lo be-kankantom. Okay, tree
gum. ולא בקנקנתום ve-lo be-kankantom which also I don't know how they
translate that.
Copper sulphate, if that helps.
There you go. Which is also some type of an ink. ולא
בכל דבר שרושם. ve-lo be-chol davar she-roshem.
Nothing which leaves a mark, which means what? It means indelible, indelible
mark. Which means when you write on the parchment, does it get
absorbed into the parchment so even if you were to scrape it
off you would be left with the mark, or is it basically
a type essentially of a paint that sits on the surface of
the parchment that doesn't get absorbed so you can scrape it off
and nothing's left behind, which is what our ספרי תורה sifrei torah
are written on, which is how you can make a... how you
can fix it because you can scrape it off, right? Okay,
אלא בדיו. ela be-deyo. It has to be our ink, which basically
sits on the top but doesn't get absorbed into the parchment. שנאמר
ומחה. she-ne'emar u-macha. You have to erase, scrape it off. כתב שיכול
להמחות. ketav she-yachol le-himachot. It has to be able to be erasable.
Which presumably means like of course if you couldn't erase it at
all, then you wouldn't be able to do the פסוק, pasuk but
presumably even if there was something you could scrape off, it has
to be fully erasable. It can't leave anything behind. The whole words
have to flow into as it were, you know, into the water.
Okay, so now there's a lot of big תוספות Tosafots in here,
not a lot of גמרא, Gemara so we'll get through the דף
daf quicker but then I'll tell you a little bit about what
the תוספות Tosafot says. אמר רבא, Amar Rava,
מגילת סוטה שכתבה בלילה פסולה. megillat sotah she-ketavah ba-laylah pesulah. If you
wrote it at night it's
invalid. מאי טעמא? mai ta'ama?
What? Doesn't sound like you have to do it on the spot.
Yeah, but... but yes, but we'll get to that. We're... we're going
to explain a lot of things. We'll get... we'll get to that.
מאי טעמא? mai ta'ama? אתיא תורה תורה. atya torah-torah. כתיב הכא ועשה
לה הכהן את כל התורה הזאת ketiv hacha ve-asah lah ha-kohen et
kol ha-torah ha-zot that you should do this entire instruction or teaching.
וכתיב התם על פי התורה אשר יורוך ועל המשפט. ve-ketiv hatam al
pi ha-torah asher yoru-cha ve-al ha-mishpat. Based on the תורה that they
teach you. This is by the בית דין הגדול Beitin ha-Gadol when
they're being challenged by the זקן ממרא. zaken mamre. You shall follow
the instruction that they teach you. מה משפט ביום אף מגילת סוטה
ביום. ma mishpat ba-yom af megillat sotah ba-yom. The same way judgment
takes place in the day, even the מגילת סוטה megillat sotah takes
place during the day. Judgment does not take place at night. I'm
going to read a little bit more and then I want to
sort of tell you a little bit what תוספות Tosafot says about
each one of these. כתבה
למפרע פסולה. ketavah le-mafrea pesulah. Let's say you wrote it backwards, which
means maybe the words appeared on the מגילה Megillah. in order but
you started at the end and you wrote backwards. Okay, so you
wrote, you had your whole מגילה megillah and you were sort of
at the bottom of the line, you wrote the last word, then
the second to last word, you know, so maybe in the end
it reads correctly, but the order that you wrote it was you
wrote it backwards. Okay.
Maybe it makes it that you have enough space? I don't know
why you'd do that.
It writes the last word at
the end. Oh, that's interesting. Okay, that's interesting. Okay, דכתיב deksiv וכתב
את האלות האלה. vekasav es ha'alos ha'eleh. So write these כהיכי דכתיבי,
keheichi deksiva, write them the way they're written, write them in order.
כתבה קודם שתקבל עליה השבועה, kasvah kodem shetikabel aleha hashevuah, let's say
now here's the part that skipped our משנה. Mishnah The תורה says
he makes her swear, she says and then he writes it down.
Our משנה Mishnah completely skipped over him making her swear. And now
this tells you that actually if you did what the משנה Mishnah
said, essentially, if you wrote it before she swore, it's invalid. You
have to follow the order of the פסוק. pasuk First she has
to take the oath and then you write it
down. כתבה קודם שתקבל עליה השבועה פסולה, kasvah kodem shetikabel aleha hashevuah
pesulah, שנאמר והשביע ואחר כך וכתב. shene'emar vehishbia ve'achar kach vekasav. It
has to be written after. כתבה אגרת פסולה. kasvah igheres pesulah. If
you wrote it as a letter, it's invalid. Now what does a
letter mean? So רש״י Rashi says it means without שירטוט. shirtut. שירטוט
shirtut is the scoring. I don't know if you ever look closely
at a ספר תורה, Sefer Torah, you see that there are these
like sort of, you know, sort of like
indented lines. Yeah, מגילה. megillah They're scores. Right. And they actually go,
we usually write our words on top of the line. Actually it
goes,
actually you write in the scoring, the words go below the line.
It hangs from the lines, right. Exactly. Anyway if you wrote it
without the scoring, that's how רש״י Rashi reads as a letter, it's
invalid. בספר אמרה רחמנא, basefer amrah Rachmana, it has to be like
a normal ספר and רש״י Rashi says it means like ספרי קודש
Sifrei Kodesh or whatever which are written with scoring. Okay we'll read
a little bit more on יח עמוד א yud ches amud aleph
and then talk a little bit about what the תוספות Tosfos says.
כתבה בשני דפין פסולה, kasvah bishnei dapin pesulah, if it's written on
two separate pieces of parchment, you know, you didn't have a big
enough piece of parchment so you said please continue on side two
or whatever, you know, see page two, then it's invalid. ספר אחד
אמרה רחמנא ולא שנים ושלושה ספרים,
Sefer echad
amrah
Rachmana velo shenayim ushloshah sefarim, only one book. Okay. כתב אות אחת
ומחק אות אחת וכתב אות אחת
ומחק אות אחת פסולה. kasav os achas umachak os achas vekasav os
achas umachak os achas pesulah.
You write one word, you scrape it off. You write the next
word, you scrape it off. So you're writing it in order but
you never have the whole thing present at one time.
You had a really small piece of parchment.
Oh, that's good. Maybe that's why. Okay. That's invalid. דכתיב ועשה לה
כהן את כל התורה הזאת. deksiv ve'asah lah Kohen es kol haTorah
ha'zos. Somehow it has to be the whole תורה, the whole thing
at once and then scraped off. Now what are all these, that
was pretty easy. What are all these big תוספותים Tosfosim in the
path? Okay. So,
so the one תוספות Tosfos about, just to tell you, לא על
הלוח, lo al haluach, תוספות Tosfos discusses,
you know, that in other places we actually say that other forms
of writing surfaces are okay. Think about a גט. get The גט
get says וכתב, vekasav, right, ספר כריתות Sefer Kerisus and we said
a minute ago, yesterday, you could write it on any type of
a surface. How come here we read בספר? basefer? So תוספות Tosfos
tries to figure that out. One distinction תוספות Tosfos points out to
is the word בספר, basefer, in a book, meaning that we're focusing
on the physical object of the book and that has to be
considered a classic book. So whereas by the גט get it says,
it says, what is
it? וכתב לה ספר כריתות. vekasav lah Sefer Kerisus. So it doesn't
say בספר, basefer, but a ספר כריתות Sefer Kerisus and therefore one
of the classic דרשות drashos of the rabbis is ספירת דברים בעלמא.
sepiras devarim be'alma. So meaning the word ספר there almost means like
a story of divorce as opposed to a in a book. Okay,
even when you say a book of divorce, it more relates to
what's being told about and not the physical object the same way
בספר. basefer. If you're physicalness, you can't
write a גט on a קרן פרה? keren parah?
Rashi,
okay, there are very small limitations because it has to be like
תלוש talush or whatever, but you basically don't have the limit of
the emphasis of like parchment. Because the one distinction is the word
ב. bet. Now how about the next thing about,
one minute, hold on, let me just take a look.
Oh, so in the ירושלמי Yerushalmi by the way, it has another
interesting question about whether you can write on parchment from non-kosher animals.
Okay. And one of the reasons you can't write on parchment for
non-kosher animals is because that let's say the woman refuses, changes her
mind and you're not going to erase the name, do you want
to left leave God's name on a piece of parchment from a
non-kosher animal? That's somehow seen as unseemly. Okay, but that's one question.
Another interesting question the ירושלמי Yerushalmi asks is before you erase God's
name, did this piece of parchment have קדושת ספר kedushas Sefer on
it? And one of the halachic נפקא מינה'ס nafka minas is if
you touch it does it cause impurity to the hands? That's the
classic way of testing if somebody has a type of a קדושת
ספר, kedushas Sefer, right? You'd have to, I don't know, would you
have to put it in גניזה? genizah? What would you do if
the woman said no? Okay, so that's like another question that the
ירושלמי Yerushalmi asks. It says maybe it doesn't have קדושת ספר kedushas
Sefer because if it's written for the purpose of being erased, it
doesn't have that same like, you know. status. So anyway, that's one
area of question. Okay, now, the other issue interestingly about משפט, mishpat,
that it has to be ביום. bayom. If you take a look
at תוספות, Tosfot, it is one, two, four lines down, cause the
question is: What's ביום? bayom? דיני נפשות dinei nefashot capital crimes are
always ביום. bayom. Okay, דיני ממונות dinei mamonot begin at the day
but end at night. So let's say for סוטה, Sotah, what type
of—no, I'm sorry, they're allowed to end at night. So by a
סוטה, Sotah, if we're only learning out that it's written in the
day because it says משפט, mishpat, what if you, I don't know,
started writing it in the day and ended writing it at night?
Would it be like דיני ממונות dinei mamonot or דיני נפשות? dinei
nefashot? So anyway, תוספות Tosfot says four lines down in the wide
lines near the end like directly over the word דכתיב, dechtiv, he
says ונראה דכל דין סוטה בין גמר בין תחילה פסול בלילה. venirah
dechol din Sotah bein gmar bein techilah pasul balaylah.
Any aspect of סוטה Sotah whether the beginning or the end of
the process is invalid at night. דמיא לדיני נפשות. damya ledinei nefashot.
So not like דיני ממונות. dinei mamonot. דתחילת דין ביום אבל גמר
דין אפילו בלילה. detchilat din bayom aval gmar din afilu balaylah.
So I think again, the fact that סוטה Sotah is דיני נפשות
dinei nefashot goes back to a theme we've been talking about, right?
Do you see this as a, you know, you are in a
way you are adjudicating, right, her whether she's חייב מיתה chayav mitah
or not? Because if she's found guilty and the water does it,
she's actually going to, not according to the פסוקים psukim that she'll
die, but חז"ל Chazal understand that she'll die, right? So again, framing
it as a דיני נפשות dinei nefashot I felt was very interesting
in terms of the theme that we've been dealing with. Okay, now,
another interesting point about תוספות Tosfot is, wait
a minute,
yes, wait a minute,
about this issue about wait a minute, about this idea that if
you go out of order, because if if he makes her, if
he writes it before making her take the oath and everything has
to be exactly in the order. Is the ירושלמי Yerushalmi here of
a קופסא? kufsa?
Yes. So תוספות Tosfot says, wait
a minute,
so תוספות Tosfot has a question why some places like it doesn't
emphasize the order if the order is מעכב. me'akev. And if you
take a look, the line starts with the words ונראה דלא חשיב.
venirah delo chashiv. It's like four lines before the תוספות Tosfot סברא
sevara
begins or maybe three lines. Right beginning of the line is ונראה
ד. venirah de. People see that? Yeah. So it says ונראה דלא
חשיב אלא היכא דכתיבנא על הסדר אבל סדר סוטה אינו נשנה על
הסדר. venirah delo chashiv ela heicha dechtivna al haseder aval seder Sotah
eino nishneh al haseder. That I wanted to point this out to
you again, point we've seen before. The order of סוטה Sotah mentioned
in the משניות Mishnayot is not necessarily the exact order that it
has to be done. Yes, סוטה Sotah has to be done in
the precise order, but the precise order of the
פסוקים, psukim, ironically not the precise order of the
משניות. Mishnayot. שהרי אין סדר משנה וסדר פרשה מכוונים כמו שפירשנו בראש
הפרק. sheharei ein seder Mishnah veseder parashah mechuvannim kemo shepeirashnu berosh haperek.
Right? Just consider it. Our משנה Mishnah spoke about writing it before
it spoke about having her take the oath. And we just said
explicitly that if you wrote it before the oath, it's
invalid. וסדר הפרשה עיקר אבל סדר המשנה אפילו למצוה בעלמא לא. veseder
haparashah ikkar aval seder haMishnah afilu lemitzvah be'alma lo. Okay? So it's
very bizarre. The order of the משנה Mishnah is not is not
precise, and it's actually the wrong order. And according to what we
just read, if you follow the order of the משנה Mishnah and
you wrote the מגילה megillah. before having her take the oath, the
מגילה megillah would be invalid.
Okay? Get the order of the משנה is not determined by what
we would say is the halachic requirement? I don't know about not
determined.
He's just saying right, he's just saying some other principle that—yeah, exactly.
The order of the משנה reflects maybe certain literary or other concerns,
but it is not to be read halachically. And I mean the
big evidence is that the משנה didn't mention her taking the oath,
and we just said that if you wrote it before taking the
oath it's invalid. Now this last תוספות, Tosfot, this huge one, okay,
which is about when do you need שרטוט shirtut or not? Right?
If the idea is that you can't write it without the scoring,
תוספות Tosfot has a problem. Like why did you need a פסוק
pasuk to tell you that? There's another גמרא Gemara at the beginning
of גיטין Gittin that basically says it's forbidden to write even three
words from a פסוק pasuk without scoring, I mean without the lines.
Even if you're not writing it as a ספר, you're just writing
somebody a letter. So of course you need scoring. So תוספות Tosfot
says: Yes, but let's does the fact that you're supposed to do
it wouldn't have invalidated the מגילה. megillah, Let's say you had written
it without the scoring. So we would have given you a slap
because you were supposed to write it with scoring. Great. But does
that mean the מגילה is invalid? Right? The מגילת סוטה? megillat Sotah?
No. That you need a special פסוק pasuk. to tell you even
as an object of a מגילה, absent the scoring, it's not good.
So even if there's a general requirement to do it, it didn't—wouldn't
have meant that the object is necessarily invalid. And then תוספות Tosfot
goes and tries to figure out when do you need scoring when
you don't, because the גמרא Gemara, makes it sound like you don't
need it by תפילין, tefillin, but he's very bothered if there's an
idea that any פסוק pasuk. you write needs scoring, how can we
do it in תפילין tefillin without? He develops an idea of two
types of scoring. One is the frame around the whole section, which
he says that would be suffice for this requirement of not writing
any even three words of a פסוק pasuk without it. And then
there's the scoring
of
each— line at the very end of תוספות Tosafot and he says
the following. He says, he says like this. He says, מצאתי בתוספות
רבנו Matsati b'Tosafot Rabbeinu י"ב א'. Yud Beit Aleph.
I don't know who that is, יצחק בן אברם Yitzchak ben Avram
maybe. It's like three lines before the תוספות Tosafot כתב, Ktav, like
six lines from the bottom near the beginning of the line. People
see this, מצאתי, Matsati, seven lines from the end? Yeah.
מצאתי בתוספות רבנו,
Matsati b'Tosafot Rabbeinu, I don't know, also יצחק בן אברם, Yitzchak ben
Avram, מסכת גיטין. Masechet Gittin.
ששמע מרבי אליהו הצרפתי שהיה אומר: Sheshama me'Rabbi Eliyahu haTzarfati shehaya omer:
מה שאנו כותבים בכתבים בלא שירטוט. ma she'anu kotvim b'ktavim b'lo sirtut.
We write in like in our you know correspondence we quote פסוקים,
pesukim, you know דברי שלום ואמת, Divei Shalom ve'Emet, let's say you
write at the top of a letter as a way you know
you just write it as a nice flowery language but you're quoting
a part of a פסוק. pasuk ליכא למיחש, Lekka le-mimchash, you don't
have to
worry דלא כתבינא לשום פסוק. d'lo katvina leshum pasuk. We're not writing
it as a פסוק. pasuk אלא אמירה בעלמא לפרוש בשלום בלשון עברי,
Ela amira be'alma lifrosh b'shalom belashon Ivri, right, to open in a
nice poetic way, we're not directly saying the פסוק pasuk, says, we're
like echoing a פסוק pasuk, as it were. או לדבר בלשון צח,
O ledaber belashon tzach, to use it as a flowery language.
אבל כשכותב שמביא אותו לשם פסוק, Aval k'shekosev shemevi oto leshem pasuk,
if you're writing it and let's say you're writing a letter and
you want to say, 'Just like the פסוק pasuk. says,' and then
you're going to quote the פסוק, pasuk then כי האי גוונא אסור
למכתב בלא שירטוט, ki hai gavna assur lemichtav belo sirtut, then you
can't write it without scoring. So that's the quote. Then תוספות Tosafot
says, ולא ידענא מנלן למכתב בפירושין פסוקים בלא שירטוט כשמביא לשם פסוק.
v'lo yadana minan limichtav be'peirushin pesukim belo sirtut k'shemevi leshem pasuk. Then
תוספות Tosafot says, I don't get it, all the commentaries we write,
if we're writing a commentary on the תורה, we're writing a commentary
on the גמרא, Gemara like if I actually quote פסוקים pesukim as
part of my discussion, I'm telling you I don't do שירטוט. sirtut.
How am I allowed to do that without the שירטוט? sirtut? So
it's an actual interesting question of like how we satisfy you know
that requirement of doing the שירטוט. sirtut. And actually, I'm sorry Michael
wasn't here because he raised the question about you know is the
opinion earlier that you have to quote the middle of the פסוק,
pasuk? a problem of כל פסוק דלא פסקי משה, kol pasuk d'lo
paskei Moshe, you're not supposed to split a פסוק. pasuk So רב
עובדיה יוסף Rav Ovadia Yosef has a תשובה teshuvah about that about
like are you allowed to—this isn't the same but it's parallel to
this question of quoting פסוקים pesukim do you have to do שירטוט.
sirtut. If we're having a conversation and I'm quoting a פסוק pasuk
and you know when I say, 'Well what do you mean, it
says like ואנכי עפר ואפר,' va-anochi afar va-efer, was I allowed to
do that because I didn't quote the whole פסוק? pasuk, I maybe
had to say, 'Doesn't it say ויאמר אברהם אל ה' ואנכי
עפר—' va-yomer Avraham el Hashem va-anochi afar like when we you know
when we quote פסוקים pesukim we quote parts of פסוקים pesukim and
are you allowed also to like say שם ה' Shem Hashem if
you're quoting only a partial פסוק or whatever. So רב עובדיה יוסף
Rav Ovadia Yosef has a תשובה teshuvah about this and he says
all you have to do is read the גמרא Gemara to see
that the גמרא is quoting partial פסוקים pesukim with שם ה' Shem
Hashem and it's not a problem. So basically he says the idea
of כל פסוק דלא פסקי משה kol pasuk d'lo paskei Moshe does
not prohibit that, that more sort of speaks about reading a פסוק
in a type of a ritual context which might have been the
similar to the case about the מגילת סוטה. Megillat Sotah. That was
an actual ritual context, that might be the restriction that you can't
do a partial פסוק, but in a type of a conversation, learning
and so on, you would not have that restriction, but תוספות Tosafot
is still bothered but where's the שירטוט sirtut and he sort of
leaves it as a question.
Yeah, I always thought that much of the correspondence of